Another form of normalization covered in the exam
topics is third normal form (3NF). In third normal
form, a value change in a non-key column in one
table should not necessitate a change in another
non-key column elsewhere, as this can cause
problems with historical data. That sounds
like a lot, so let's see an example of this.
I have a small sample of products with prices.
Sometimes, these products go on sale. What
do you think would happen if I changed one
of these prices in the price column? Every order
referencing this product would be wrong because
if there were an orders table referencing
this list, all of the prices in every order
would change. This example demonstrates
a value change in one non-key column
necessitating a change in another non-key column.
Thus, there are two plausible solutions. Either
the price of a product needs to be adjustable
when placing an order, or we would need a sale
price column, which I will add, that will have a
sale price we can use when products go on sale.
Of course, this would mean that each
product can only have one sale price,
so it may be better to allow price
adjustments in an orders table. The point
is that we do not want one change triggering
unexpected changes elsewhere in a database.